<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE organisations SYSTEM "wxperl.dtd">

<!-- data from apps.txt -->
<organisations>
  <organisation>
    <name>Wordit Limited</name>
    <site>http://www.wordit.com/</site>
    <country>UK</country>
    <contact>
      <name>Marcus Friedlaender</name>
      <email>info@wordit.com</email>
    </contact>
    <wxperl>
      <rating>5</rating>
      <comments>
A most excellent GUI. I've used Perl/Tk and Win32::GUI, and find
wxPerl superior in feature-set and code structure.
      </comments>
    </wxperl>

    <applications>
      <application>
        <name>Prima</name>
        <site>http://www.wordit.com/prima/</site>
        <license-type><commercial /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version>0.12</wxperl-version>
        <domain>Information managers</domain>
        <short-description>
Wordit Prima makes databases as easy as web browsing by combining a
database with a web browser.
        </short-description>
        <long-description>
Wordit Prima makes databases as easy as web browsing by combining a
database with a web browser. Instead of the usual tree lists in most
programs, there's no scrolling through branches, and any entry can
have as many parent categories as you want. You can create graphs and
web sites of databases with a single click!  Uses: Outlining
documents, such as letters, essays, theses Planning and creating web
sites Brainstorming Addressbooks. Create links between people, and
store detailed notes, and pictures Storing web browser bookmarks Music
collections, i.e. launch your MP3 files from prima Picture
collections. Store your photo collections with descriptions and links
and for organizing any kind of information.
        </long-description>
      </application>

      <application>
        <name>UploadAway</name>
        <site>http://www.uploadaway.com/</site>
        <license-type><commercial /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version>0.13</wxperl-version>
        <domain>FTP/Website Management</domain>
        <short-description>
UploadAway is an automated uploading utility. Swiftly update an entire
web site with one click. Supports multiple sites. Automatic chmod of
executables, conversion of spaces to underscores, and upper to
lower-case characters in filenames.
        </short-description>
        <long-description>
Swiftly update an entire web site with one click.  UploadAway is an
automated file uploading utility for web authors. Supports multiple
sites. All you have to do is tell UploadAway where your files on your
computer are, where you want the files to go on your web server, and
your FTP login details. That's all!  One click, and let UploadAway
take it away.  No more searching for files in your FTP client, no more
clicking single files, no more clicking through directories, no more
searching for the files you just updated.  Web developers will
appreciate UploadAway's following advanced options: Automatic chmod of
executables on Unix-like servers, conversion of spaces to underscores,
conversion of filenames with upper-case characters to all lower-case.
        </long-description>
      </application>
    </applications>
  </organisation>

  <organisation>
    <name>pVoice Software</name>
    <site>http://www.pvoice.org/</site>
    <country>The Netherlands</country>
    <contact>
      <name>Jouke Visser</name>
      <email>jouke@pvoice.org</email>
    </contact>
    <wxperl>
      <rating>4.5</rating>
      <comments>It's *the* GUI of choice for Perl!</comments>
    </wxperl>

    <applications>
      <application>
        <name>pVoice</name>
        <site>http://www.pvoice.org/pvoice.html</site>
        <license-type><open-source /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version>0.12</wxperl-version>
        <domain>Augmentive and Assistive Communications</domain>
        <short-description>
pVoice is an application for severely disabled children who can use 
it to speak by selecting symbols and/or photos.
        </short-description>
      </application>

      <application>
        <name>pType</name>
        <site>http://www.pvoice.org/ptype.html</site>
        <license-type><open-source /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version>0.12</wxperl-version>
        <domain>Augmentive and Assistive Communications</domain>
        <short-description>
pType is an application for severely disabled children who can use it 
to learn how to write by selecting letters and form words (a kind of an 
on-screen keyboard)
        </short-description>
      </application>
    </applications>
  </organisation>

  <organisation>
    <name>Journal and Courier</name>
    <site>http://www.jconline.com/</site>
    <country>United States</country>
    <contact>
      <name>Joseph Youngquist</name>
      <email>jyoungquist@journalandcourier.com</email>
    </contact>
    <wxperl>
      <rating>5</rating>
      <comments>
I choose to re-write the online production tool to utilize the
features present in wxPerl.  The main feature used is the Wx::Grid
control.  This single control was the main drive to make the switch
from Win32::GUI to wxPerl.  Once into the development with wxPerl, the
benefits of the tool kit were really understood.  Speed, memory usage,
look and feel of the controls, the vast choice in controls to use all
are first rate.  The learning curve for me was about a month, and by
this, I mean it took me a month to completely tweak the new interface
for our production tool - very similar to the time it took me to do
the Win32 version the first time.  I had no prior wxWindows
experience.
    The documentation for the Perl aspects of wxWindows needs some
work (updating) but once you ignore "wxPerl note: This method is not
implemented in wxPerl" your ok, and the documentation for the
wxWindows aspects translate directly 99% of the time.
    All in all, this is the best GUI toolkit for Perl in my opinion
and this comes from using Win32 and Tk.
      </comments>
    </wxperl>

    <applications>

      <application>
        <name>Online Production Tool</name>
        <license-type><commercial /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version>0.15</wxperl-version>
        <domain>Online News Site Production</domain>
        <short-description>
A GUI for Newsroom copy editors to publish the online portion of the
daily news to the paper's website.  The application handles the
generation of HTML syntax, photo/image resizing and positioning as
well as the uploading of all HTML source pages and their images.
        </short-description>
        <long-description>
The Online Production Tool was developed from the need to have news
content updated by our newsroom employees, who have no web programming
knowledge what so ever.  The technical aptitude for html markup, image
processing, folder structures and FTP are none existent and thus
needed to be removed from the users need to have to deal with.  The
other requirements were to be as extendable as possible, being able to
add additional online components (new sections, article types, etc.,)
with the minimal amount of reprogramming as possible - 90% database
driven.  With the wxPerl version of the production tool, the interface
allows users to quickly place articles to page fronts and sections,
change headline text, article types (columns, letters to the editor,
etc.) as well as change the articles type all together, sports to a
business article for example.  Also with the wxPerl version of the
application, networking the client GUI was possible, allowing the work
load to be distributed to the main editors - who all use Macs but the
Online department all use PCs.
        </long-description>
      </application>

    </applications>
  </organisation>

  <organisation>
    <name>VisualWx team</name>
    <site>http://visualwx.altervista.org/</site>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <contact>
      <name>Antonio</name>
      <email>visualwx@katamail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <wxperl>
      <rating>4</rating>
      <comments>
      </comments>
    </wxperl>

    <applications>

      <application>
        <name>VisualWx</name>
        <site>http://visualwx.altervista.org/</site>
        <license-type><freeware /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version>Any</wxperl-version>
        <domain></domain>
        <short-description>
Rad &amp; Gui Editor for wxPerl
        </short-description>
        <long-description>
        </long-description>
      </application>

    </applications>
  </organisation>

<!-- template
  <organisation>
    <name></name>
    <site></site>
    <country></country>
    <contact>
      <name></name>
      <email></email>
    </contact>
    <wxperl>
      <rating></rating>
      <comments>
      </comments>
    </wxperl>

    <applications>

      <application>
        <name></name>
        <site></site>
        <license-type><commercial /><open-source /><freeware /></license-type>
        <platforms>
          <windows />
          <linux />
        </platforms>
        <wxperl-version></wxperl-version>
        <domain></domain>
        <short-description>
        </short-description>
        <long-description>
        </long-description>
      </application>

    </applications>
  </organisation>
-->

</organisations>
